<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Squad Wipe</title>
    <description>Instant gaming articles.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2016 21:40:16 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 May 2016 21:40:16 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The end of the Xbox 360 marks the end of an era</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On the 20th April, in a post titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.xbox.com/2016/04/20/xbox-360-celebrating-10-years/&quot;&gt;“Achievement Unlocked: 10 Years – Thank You, Xbox 360”&lt;/a&gt;, Microsoft announced that they would stop manufacturing Xbox 360 consoles. This of course isn’t particularly surprising, and I think we’re all gladly optimistic about what the future will bring for the Xbox platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But much like the consoles that preceded it, the 360 will enter the crypt of games history alongside many of the titles that made it so popular. Whether we like it or not, games that mesmerised, astounded and entertained us &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past weekend I’ve been staying with my parents in their new house and have had the pleasure of replaying titles that I haven’t had access to in over year. These include both Xbox-exclusive and cross-platform games like the Call of Duty’s, Skate 2, and Halo 3. On a very personal note, these games played substantial roles in my teenage years and connected with me, in an albeit very different way to TV, cinema and literature. I think it’s fascinating how we reflect on the games of our past, often with such a great sense of nostalgia, perhaps even sadness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote-block container-constrained&quot;&gt;
	&lt;blockquote class=&quot;inline h1&quot;&gt;
		&quot;The [Xbox] 360 will enter the crypt of games history, alongside many of the titles that made it so popular.&quot;
	&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 14:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/the-end-of-360</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/the-end-of-360</guid>
        
        
        <category>comment,</category>
        
        <category>xbox</category>
        
        <category>360,</category>
        
        <category>culture</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quantum Break was the game we needed</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;And boy, did it deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quantum Break has been out on the Xbox One for about a month now, and during that period I’ve had the opportunity to replay it to my heart’s content. As a result, I’ve been able to identify what I really like about it, and what’s not so great. A major pitfall to the game however, &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; its replayability and much like all great narratives, it’s hard to re-experience something that was so memorable in the first instance. Quantum break is a game that certainly doesn’t play like anything &lt;em&gt;I’ve&lt;/em&gt; played before but if forced to, I might compare it to Max Payne 3 (another title by the creators, Remedy Entertainment), or weirdly, Star Wars Battlefront (bear with me on this one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title represents Microsoft’s continued drive towards creating content &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theverge.com/2015/12/10/9880594/microsoft-xbox-games-2016-interview-crackdown-3-quantum-break-recore&quot;&gt;exclusive to its own platforms&lt;/a&gt;. Not only is it exceptionally well-written, with brilliant acting from Shawn Ashmore and Game of Thrones actor Aidan Gillen, but it’s beautifully lit and styled. In fact Quantum Break is a game that has its own very distinct visual style, both in gameplay and menus, which although as gamers we don’t talk about much, is very important to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-pod isActive pad-20&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/quantum-break-cutscene.png&quot; class=&quot;right box-hover-shadow&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;image-caption right&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;light&quot;&gt;Quantum Break features acting performances from both Shawn Ashmore (X-men) and Aidan Gillen (Game of Thrones).&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;lightbox&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;lightbox-wrapper&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/quantum-break-cutscene.png&quot; class=&quot;lightbox-image&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;caption light&quot;&gt;Quantum Break features acting performances from both Shawn Ashmore (X-men) and Aidan Gillen (Game of Thrones).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;close&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really struck me about Quantum Break is the extent of characterisation. It’s something that forces us to develop a strong bond with the game’s key characters (including its protagonist Jack Joyce) and that Remedy really got right this time. While the script certainly contributes to this, as does the mesmerising acting by all, at certain key points we’re also forced to make decisions that will determine the path a character chooses and consequently decide the course the game takes. Science fiction storylines often fall apart when inconsistencies become apparent, but this title really holds its own. At no point did I feel that what I’d seen didn’t correspond to the world that had been laid out before us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, Quantum Break &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; like a third-person shooter, but that couldn’t be further from the truth. The game actually doesn’t &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like a shooter at all, and much of our protagonist’s power lies in his abilities, which allow us to find ways around enemies, slow them down, and kill them. While initially I found myself relying on a single ability, I found that it was possible to create ‘recipes’ for taking down multiple enemies - combinations for different situations. In this sense, the game didn’t feel repetitive or button-mashy and gave me the freedom to challenge myself and play in a way that others might not. Despite this I did find ultimately that we’re reliant upon guns to kill enemies, which often feel so dissatisfyingly weak and inaccurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote-block container-constrained&quot;&gt;
	&lt;blockquote class=&quot;inline h1&quot;&gt;
		&quot;Quantum Break has its own very distinct visual style which is very important to us as gamers.&quot;
	&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you might have already read about Quantum Break is that following these key decisions, if downloaded, we’re given a 30 minute episode of the game’s ‘TV show’. Of the times I’ve played through the game, I’ve only watched these episodes once, although I’ve been told that the episode you get to watch is based on the decision you make.
I didn’t feel they contributed much to the game’s central narrative, mostly because they follow a storyline that runs in parallel and is related to, but doesn’t affect that of the main characters (for the most part). I also felt quite aware that what I was watching wasn’t TV or an on-demand programme, but that was ‘low-key’, echoing something like the Halo web-series ‘Forward Unto Dawn’. Despite this and the 75GB file download involved, these episodes make for an enjoyable ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I probably don’t have to mention it, but as you nay have guessed Quantum Break’s visuals are a gift to behold. This manifests itself in the environments Jack navigates through: crumbling buildings, a ship tearing through a bridge, a falling crane, all in a state of either stopped in time (in so-called ‘stutters’ in which only our protagonist can traverse) or in motion; thousands of particles tracked in space. Some of these destructive environments even involve puzzles that sometimes require a little thought to pass through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-pod pad-20&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/quantum-break-show.png&quot; class=&quot;left box-hover-shadow&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;image-caption left&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;light&quot;&gt;Quantum Break also includes an on-demand TV show that runs parallel to the game&#39;s central narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;lightbox&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;lightbox-wrapper&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/quantum-break-show.png&quot; class=&quot;lightbox-image&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;caption light&quot;&gt;Quantum Break also includes an on-demand TV show that runs parallel to the game&#39;s central narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;close&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, Jack’s surroundings will often contain collectibles, recordings and messages that further shed light on the main story. These are largely worth taking the time to read and enjoy, whether they be email exchanges between main and peripheral characters, or documents referring to a backstory event. Equally as impressive is the motion tracking and model detail. Every motion in Jack’s movement, every flash of anger in his expression is identifiable  - I often found myself having to replay footage to ascertain whether it’s real or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quantum Break is proof that the traditional story-driven campaign has a large place in gaming. While the visuals are impressive, the title’s well-written script, extraordinary acting, and overall execution make it stand head and shoulders above other games in the genre. Highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 14:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/quantum-break-was-what-we-needed</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/quantum-break-was-what-we-needed</guid>
        
        
        <category>fps,</category>
        
        <category>single-player,</category>
        
        <category>story,</category>
        
        <category>non-linear,</category>
        
        <category>role-playing,</category>
        
        <category>third-person</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why Rainbow Six Siege didn&#39;t live up to the hype</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With the price having come down significantly since its launch, you can now buy Rainbow Six Siege on the main consoles for about £20 (~$28). To the average FPS gamer, this might seem like a good deal. The round-based shooter, published by Ubisoft, received a modest 7.9/10 from IGN and 8 on Gamespot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total honesty this wasn’t a game that I was hugely interested in playing on launch, but having watched the gameplay of Youtubers like Jackfrags, Rainbow Six Siege seemed like something I’d enjoy and potentially be good at. It has a large array of weapons upgrades and customisations, a selection of characters each with their own special abilities designed for different play styles, and the kind of fast-paced, close-quarters combat synonymous with Counter Strike: Global Offensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format is round-based, team gameplay, where to die means to sit out of the round until the next. I won’t lie, this can be hugely unforgiving but when you’re the last team-member the pressure is exhilarating. It is however a formula that we’ve seen before, but not in this level of detail and with such diverse, destructible environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote-block container-constrained&quot;&gt;
	&lt;blockquote class=&quot;inline h1&quot;&gt;
		&quot;...there&#39;s such a great emphasis on teamwork, flanking and strategy...&quot;
	&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a number of issues plague the Rainbow Six experience. While many games give new players an arsenal of tools to help them rank up, or points to spend help them quickly buy new modifications, Rainbow Six Siege starts players on the most basic ‘Recruit’ character with no points and inaccurate, low-damage guns to start with. Because of this, players ultimately have to play for several hours before they have enough points to buy a new character. I went for ‘Sledge’ an SAS soldier with a clichéd British accent and sledgehammer that can smash through walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with this however is that only one player per team can play as a particular character, meaning if the character you decided to spend your hard-earned points on has already been picked by a teammate, you’re back to square one. It’s also hard to know which characters are less popular, and therefore have lower odds of getting picked, and which characters’ upgrades offer the best value. There’s likely to be a correlation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another major issue is that of players leaving a game lobby before it starts. Because there’s such a great emphasis on teamwork, flanking and strategy, a team of two or three players is massively disadvantaged against one of five. And what’s more, no penalties are brought against players who do this. One can only draw comparisons with a game-mode like ‘Breakout’ in Halo 5, in which players are served warnings or even bans for quitting multiple games in a short space of time. One can’t help but feel like the game’s makers should have been a little more realistic and put restrictions in place to prevent this. Of the first ten games I played, this happened four times - I imagine my fellow teammates saw how low a level I was decided we were already fucked from the get-go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another, although perhaps less obvious issue is that to coordinate a strategy against the other team really requires some kind of communication. The majority of console gamers still don’t regularly use headsets, and you can hardly blame them. I actually came across a surprisingly few number of players with mics (about 1 in 10) and this only created the impression that other players didn’t want to help, not that they weren’t able to. In fairness, RB6S does allow players to set markers and spot other players on the map, and killed players can use CCTV to identify enemy team members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-pod pad-20&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/rainbow-six-lineup.jpg&quot; class=&quot;left box-hover-shadow&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;image-caption left&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;light&quot;&gt;Rainbow Six Siege features a selection of characters each with their own special abilities designed for different play styles. Choose wisely.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;lightbox&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;lightbox-wrapper&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/rainbow-six-lineup.jpg&quot; class=&quot;lightbox-image&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;caption light&quot;&gt;Rainbow Six Siege features a selection of characters each with their own special abilities designed for different play styles. Choose wisely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;close&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I really wanted to enjoy Rainbow Six Siege, I found that several underlying flaws prevented me from getting into it, notably the ability to abandon the lobby before a game starts without penalty. I therefore can’t guarantee that if you’re a fan of CS:GO or round-based gameplay you’ll enjoy this too. RB6S is a game for the hardcore FPS-ers but can be incredibly unforgiving if you expect to be able to rank up like you can in other successful franchises. But there’s no denying, those environments are practically works of destructible, chaotic art.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2016 14:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/rainbow-six-siege</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/rainbow-six-siege</guid>
        
        
        <category>fps,</category>
        
        <category>team-based,</category>
        
        <category>round-based</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Star Wars Battlefront power-ups: a primer</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With Star Wars: Battlefront having been in the public domain for almost half a year now, it’s been interesting to see how the press have reported on its two DLC launches and whether gamers have returned to the old favourites, or stuck it out and endured the changes. Of course, much like DICE has done with Battlefield, many of the game’s weapons have been made less powerful under the banner of ‘balancing’. For many I think this has been a major deterrent, especially for new players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internet’s response to the game’s first DLC download ‘The Battle of Jakku’ was a great big ‘meh’, and the newest release ‘Outer Rim’ doesn’t seem to have stirred a great deal of interest (with no new Walker Assault maps), but I think there’s still hope left in the galaxy for this franchise, especially with ‘bonus points weekends’, and ‘Jabba the Hut contracts’. For me, Battlefront is still a hell of alot of fun with a friend or two, and acts as a nice entrée into other games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-pod isActive pad-20&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/battlefront-shield.jpg&quot; class=&quot;right box-hover-shadow&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;image-caption right&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;light&quot;&gt;The squad shield makes for a great place to recharge your health bar and hide from incoming fire, including Orbital Strikes, but not grenades.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;lightbox&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;lightbox-wrapper&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/battlefront-shield.jpg&quot; class=&quot;lightbox-image&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;caption light&quot;&gt;The squad shield makes for a great place to recharge your health bar and hide from incoming fire, including Orbital Strikes, but not grenades.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;close&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to blasters and ‘cards’, Battlefront’s special purchasable weapons (grenades, torpedoes, snipers etc), the game also features ‘power-ups’ that can be found (seemingly randomly) scattered around maps. They can often be the difference between taking down an AT-AT and winning the round, or losing and incredibly useful when used strategically. Each power-up has a specific (and usually fairly obvious) purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power-ups that probably don’t require much explanation are the thermal imploder, a high explosive grenade-of-sorts, and the blaster cannon, a simple turret with front-facing shield. The thermal imploder is immensely effective when used on clusters of infantry and will obliterate anything within a ~5m spread of itself. Remember to follow the explosion with blaster fire to assure your success. The cannon is really only useful against infantry in confined spaces, like the corridors on Hoth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other deployable explosive in addition to the thermal imploder, is the proximity bomb (think claymores in Battlefield 4). The proximity bomb is best used in funnels the enemy are bound to pass through, like doorways, trenches and crevasses. Although I’ve never seen the proximity bomb kill more than a single soldier, its splash damage does mean it’s possible to score multiple kills with follow up fire. I usually place my proximity bombs and forget about them, only to score a kill later in the round. A nice addition, but by no means the most powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The autonomous power-ups (ones that you can leave to do the killing) include a sensor droid (which comes in Empire and Rebel variants), infantry turret, and the vehicle turret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote-block container-constrained&quot;&gt;
	&lt;blockquote class=&quot;inline h1&quot;&gt;
		&quot;Place the [infrantry] turret in one of the many cutthroughs, just behind the middle ridgeline on Tattooine...&quot;
	&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Empire variant of the sensor droid fires lasers at a relatively low rate that take about 20% health. The Rebel variant simply scans its vicinity for enemies. The droids are most useful if you’re trying to defend an objective and are being attacked from multiple sides. While neither deal substantial damage, their thick armour ensures an attacking player’s presence will be known to your teammates should they try to destroy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The infantry turret is one of the most underrated power-ups in the game. While its range isn’t so great, when placed in a strategically important position the turret can allow a player to get several kills. A favourite play of mine is to place the turret in one of the many cutthroughs, just behind the middle ridgeline on Tattooine. The turret’s effectiveness here lies in the fact that the enemy can’t see it before they’re in its range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the vehicle turret, although harder to place than the infantry turret is to destroy AT-AT and AT-STs. Because AT-ATs follow a predictable path, it’s most likely that you’ll place it well before the vehicle is within range. Be sure to conceal its location so that it can’t be spotted by infantry and destroyed. On Endor, Walker Assault, the vehicle turret is ideally placed along the river that spans the map. On Hoth, try placing the turret in a trench, out of sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power-up that Battlefront players yearn to use most is the Orbital Strike, probably because of its perceived damage. Players are given a pair of electrobinoculars and a hail of lasers will splash down on the area they designate. The orbital strike is a little overrated, and has been weakened since launch but is still effective on maps with wide spaces with no cover (not Jakku or Endor). Be aware of the fact that the opposing team are warned before an incoming strike and will move out of the way of its destruction. However, the weapon is immensely destructive when used on AT-ATs on Walker Assault while their shields are down. The real skill in using the Orbital Strike is in waiting for the opportune moment to strike. Be patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-pod pad-20&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/battlefront-orbital.jpg&quot; class=&quot;left box-hover-shadow&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;image-caption left&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;light&quot;&gt;Be aware when using the Orbital Strike that the opposing team are warned beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;lightbox&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;lightbox-wrapper&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/battlefront-orbital.jpg&quot; class=&quot;lightbox-image&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;caption light&quot;&gt;Be aware when using the Orbital Strike that the opposing team are warned beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;close&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last two power-ups are the smart rocket and squad shield. The former serves very much the same purpose as the vehicle turret. A direct hit to the disk-shape on the front of an AT-AT will most likely give you an assist should your team bring it down - the same goes for the AT-ST. The latter is best used when attacking an objective, but not on the objective itself. The flaw in this power-up that most new players don’t realise is that grenades can pass easily through it and explode within. Additionally, the opposing team will often breach and shield and attempt a melee. Deploy the shield when an orbital strike is incoming and there’s no obvious cover or when you need 360 degree protection from snipers and vehicles - a good example of this being the closing stages of Walker Assault and Turning Point on Tattooine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is that power-ups should ultimately be used in the context of a greater team strategy. Coordinate with your squadmates and use the above tactics to secure kills, play the objective and ultimately have fun.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2016 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/battlefront-powerups</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/battlefront-powerups</guid>
        
        
        <category>fps,</category>
        
        <category>star</category>
        
        <category>wars</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
